<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The engagement or declaration of the officers and souldiers of the County Palatine of Lancaster. Together with their letter to the reverend ministers of the several hundreds of that county, desiring them to publish the said declaration in their parish churches. As also the present state and condition of that county, certified in a letter to a well-affected citizen in London.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84432</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E736</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E443_22</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204732</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864196</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864196</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116419</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84432)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116419)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 70:E443[22])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The engagement or declaration of the officers and souldiers of the County Palatine of Lancaster. Together with their letter to the reverend ministers of the several hundreds of that county, desiring them to publish the said declaration in their parish churches. As also the present state and condition of that county, certified in a letter to a well-affected citizen in London.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed May 19, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Declaring their adhesion to the Solemn League and Covenant; protesting against Toleration, etc.-- Thomason catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 19".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643). --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lancaster (England : County Palatine) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116419:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ENGAGEMENT OR DECLARATION Of the Officers and Souldiers of the County Palatine of LANCASTER.</p>
            <p>Together with their LETTER to the Reverend Miniſters of the ſeveral Hundreds of that County, deſiring them to publiſh the ſaid DECLARATION in their Pariſh Churches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As alſo</hi> The preſent State and Condition of that County, certified in a LETTER to a well affected Citizen in LONDON.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed <hi>May</hi> 19, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:116419:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:116419:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have incloſed ſent you a Copy of the Declaration of our Souldiers: how far it is owned you may diſcern; at the next generall meeting it is expected to be ſigned by all. We are gathering into a body for our own defence. And if the news which came laſt night be true, the Enemy is marched in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our County with a Body of Horſe: our Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diery apprehend themſelves in great ſtraights; for if the Army come down, and they joyn with them to ſuppreſſe the Cavaliers, they fear, and are very jealous that the Army will afterwards fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and ſuppreſſe them. I cannot tell, but it is conceived by many well-affected to the Cauſe we firſt engaged in, that if the Parliament do not new modell the Army, and diſplace ſuch as are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally odious to the Kingdom, there will ſcarce ever be an happy peace and ſettlement in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For ſhould the Presbyterian party and the Sectaries joyn to ſuppreſſe the common Enemy, it is (I ſay) very much to be feared they would after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards claſh one with another: for when thoſe that adhere to the Covenant are put into a poſture
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116419:3"/> of defence, they will never (I am confident) lay down arms to become tame ſlaves to the Sectaries, who for all their ſpecious pretences, and flattering propoſals, have not hitherto really acted any one thing whereby our diſtractions may be removed, and Truth and Peace, which is the deſire of all good men, may be perfectly accompliſhed. We are here wonderfull inquiſitive after your Affairs in the City: we ſay here, that if you act vigorouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and improve all fair means and opportunities, as every day God begins now to put into your hands, you will give life to the whole Kingdom. I beſeech you in your next acquaint us what is done in altering your <hi>Militia,</hi> whether the City have the Tower in their poſſeſſion. If you be not more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive then ſome repreſent you in their Letters, we fear that you are onely doing what will ſerve to juſtifie your enemies in deſtroying of you. But I hope better things, which is the daily prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithfull and moſt affectionate Friend to ſerve you.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:116419:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe too frequent declenſions of many that pretend to Religion from their firſt principles, the miſunderſtanding, and diverſe interpretations of our ſolemn League and Covenant, as it may ſuit to private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſts, and the Generall Apoſtaſy of the age we live in, together with the greivous aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions under which we ſuffer, hath enforced us to preſent you with this incloſed Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein we know well the weakneſſe of the Language, and the miſcarriages that may be in the ſtile; But we intreat you, to take well the integrity of our intentionsin Conſcience of our duty; And much deſire if you think fit, to publiſh it in your congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations to the ſatisfaction of all to whom it
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116419:4"/> may come, of our fidelity, And we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maine,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Bolton <date>May 9, 1648</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your very affectionate friends &amp; ſervants
<list>
                     <item>Nich. Shuttleworth</item>
                     <item>Hugh Bradſhaw</item>
                     <item>Vghtred Shuttlewort<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>James Chanbrell</item>
                     <item>Richard Radclyffe</item>
                     <item>John Aſhurſt</item>
                     <item>Henry Porter</item>
                     <item>George Key</item>
                     <item>W. Weſt</item>
                     <item>J. Butterworth</item>
                     <item>Alex. Tompſon</item>
                     <item>Samuel Birth</item>
                     <item>William Emott</item>
                     <item>William Waller</item>
                     <item>William Gardner</item>
                     <item>Thomas Weſtmor</item>
                     <item>George Cranage.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>For the Reverend the Miniſters in the ſeverall Hundreds of the County Palatine of <hi>Lancaſter.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:116419:4"/>
            <head>The Declaration of the Officers and Souldiers of the County-Palatine of <hi>LANCASTER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHereas we lately the Officers and Souldiers of the County Palatine of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> having to our beſt knowledge behaved our ſelves as becomes loyal ſubjects and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſouldiers and ſervants of God, King, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, are on the one hand aſperſed as Malignants and Enemies to the State, and fit to be diſarmed; and on the other hand, as Rebels, and Enemies to Monarchy, and the Kings Majeſtie that now is: We therefore thought it requiſite to declare and expreſſe to the Deputy. Lieutenants and Committee of this County, That we own the Solemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of the three Kingdoms in every branch of it, and will not by any combination, perſwaſion or ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, be drawn from it. And more particularly, in reference to the ſaid aſperſions, we do further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, That we ſtand for the Fundamental Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdom by King, Lords, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, according to the Laws of the Land, and the Declarations of this preſent Parliament, before our
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116419:5"/> firſt engagement: That we love, deſire, and ſhould much rejoyce in the Regal and regular Government of His Majeſtie that now is. As for Papiſts, popiſh perſons, malignant abettors of former Innovations, Uſurpations or Oppreſſions, or any other diſaffected perſons which were, are, or ſhall be in Arms to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb Religion, Righteouſneſſe, and Peace; we from the bottom of our hearts do deteſt them, and with our lives and fortunes will endeavour to oppoſe them. And we in like manner do declare againſt Toleration of Hereſie, Schiſm, Prophaneſſe, and whatſoever is contrary to ſound Doctrine and the power of Godlineſſe, ſo plainly covenanted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared againſt by the Miniſters and others of this and other Counties: Nor will we, nor (as we verily believe) the Souldiers of the County, be comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by any Gentlemen whatſoever of this County, or other Officers, which are juſtly aſperſed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline from theſe honeſt and juſt principles, and to favour Anarchy in Church or State; but will deſire, according to the General Petition of the County, for the putting of all ſuch perſons from Places and Offices of Truſt; knowing of our own knowledge, that the Kingdoms Cauſe hath been and yet is much diſadvantaged by the preferment of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and our party weakned, yea and deſerted by many, which would not have deſerted it otherwiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Our humble requeſt therefore is, to the Deputy-Lieutenants and Committee of this County, which deſire our engagement in this preſent Service, That they would receive in good part this our plain and honeſt Declaration.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
